Steve Ramirez: My first year of grad school,
ستيف راميرز: في أول سنة لي في كلية الدراسات العليا،
eating lots of Ben &amp; Jerry's
أتناول الكثير من "بن أند جيري" [مثلجات]
watching some trashy TV
و أشاهد بعض برامج التلفزيون الرديئة
and maybe, maybe listening to Taylor Swift.
و ربما، ربما أستمع إلى "تايلر سويفت" [مغنية]
I had just gone through a breakup.
لقد مررت للتو بانفصال عاطفي.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So for the longest time, all I would do
فلأطول وقت ممكن، كل ما أردت فعله
is recall the memory of this person over and over again,
هو استعادة ذكرى هذا الشخص مراراً و تكراراً
wishing that I could get rid of that gut-wrenching,
على أمل أن أستطيع التخلص من ذلك الشعور
visceral "blah" feeling.
الداخلي المثير للغثيان و السذاجة.
Now, as it turns out, I'm a neuroscientist,
الآن، كما تبيَّن، أنا عالم أعصاب،
so I knew that the memory of that person
لذا قد عرفت أن ذكرى هذا الشخص
and the awful, emotional undertones that color in that memory,
و ما يصاحبها من شعور فظيع
are largely mediated by separate brain systems.
يقوم بهما بشكل كبير نظامان دماغيان منفصلان.
And so I thought, what if we could go into the brain
و هكذا فكرت، ماذا لو استطعنا أن ندخل الدماغ
and edit out that nauseating feeling
و نتخلص من ذلك الشعور المثير للغثيان
but while keeping the memory of that person intact?
بينما نترك ذكرى ذلك الشخص دون مساس؟
Then I realized, maybe that's a little bit lofty for now.
ثم أدركت، قد تكون هذه الفكرة مبالغ فيها الآن.
So what if we could start off by going into the brain
فماذا لو استطعنا البدء بالدخول إلى الدماغ
and just finding a single memory to begin with?
و ايجاد ذكرى واحدة نبدأ بها؟
Could we jump-start that memory back to life,
هل يمكننا إحياء هذه الذاكرة،
maybe even play with the contents of that memory?
ربما أيضاً العبث بمحتويات هذا الذاكرة؟
All that said, there is one person in the entire world right now
بعد الحديث عن هذا، حالياً هناك شخص واحد في العالم أجمع
that I really hope is not watching this talk.
أتمنى بشدة ألا يكون يشاهد هذا الخطاب.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So there is a catch. There is a catch.
لكن هناك مشكلة. هناك مشكلة.
These ideas probably remind you of "Total Recall,"
هذه الأفكار على الأغلب تذكركم ب "توتال ريكول،"
"Eternal Sunshine of the Spotless Mind,"
"أيترنال سنشاين أف ذا سبوتلس مايند،"
or of "Inception."
أو ب "إنسبشن" [أفلام]
But the movie stars that we work with
لكن نجوم السينما الذين نعمل معهم
are the celebrities of the lab.
هم مشاهير المختبر.
Xu Liu: Test mice.
شو لو: فئران المختبر.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
As neuroscientists, we work in the lab with mice
بصفتنا علماء أعصاب، نحن نعمل في المختبر مع الفئران
trying to understand how memory works.
نحاول أن نفهم كيف تعمل الذاكرة.
And today, we hope to convince you that now
و اليوم، نأمل أن نقنعكم أننا الآن
we are actually able to activate a memory in the brain
بالحقيقة قادرين أن نُفَعِّل ذاكرة في الدماغ
at the speed of light.
بسرعة الضوء.
To do this, there's only two simple steps to follow.
لفعل هذا، هناك فقط خطوتين بسيطتين لنتبعهما.
First, you find and label a memory in the brain,
أولاً، جد و ضع علامة لتمييز ذاكرة في الدماغ،
and then you activate it with a switch.
و ثم فَعِّلها بمفتاح.
As simple as that.
بهذه البساطة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
SR: Are you convinced?
ستيف راميرز: هل اقتنعتم؟
So, turns out finding a memory in the brain isn't all that easy.
قد تبين أن إيجاد ذاكرة في الدماغ ليس بهذه السهولة.
XL: Indeed. This is way more difficult than, let's say,
شو لو: بالفعل. إنه أصعب بكثير من، دعنا نقول،
finding a needle in a haystack,
إيجاد إبرة في كومة قش،
because at least, you know, the needle is still something
لأنه على الأقل، كما تعلمون، مازالت الإبرة شيء
you can physically put your fingers on.
مادي يمكنك أن تضع أصابعك عليه.
But memory is not.
لكن الذاكرة ليست كذلك.
And also, there's way more cells in your brain
و أيضاً، هناك خلايا في دماغك عددها أكثر بكثير
than the number of straws in a typical haystack.
من عدد أعواد القش في كومة قش، بالعادة.
So yeah, this task does seem to be daunting.
فأجل، تبدو هذه المهمة شاقة.
But luckily, we got help from the brain itself.
لكن لحسن الحظ، لدينا مساعدة من الدماغ نفسه.
It turned out that all we need to do is basically
لقد تبين أنه كل ما يجب علينا فعله هو
to let the brain form a memory,
أن نسمح للدماغ أن يكوِّن ذاكرة،
and then the brain will tell us which cells are involved
و من ثم سوف يخبرنا الدماغ بالخلايا المشاركة
in that particular memory.
في تلك الذاكرة بالتحديد.
SR: So what was going on in my brain
ستيف: ما الذي كان يحدث في دماغي
while I was recalling the memory of an ex?
بينما كنت أتذكَّر حبيبتي السابقة؟
If you were to just completely ignore human ethics for a second
إن تجاهلت تماماً الأخلاقيات الإنسانية لثانية
and slice up my brain right now,
و قمت بتقطيع دماغي إلى شرائح الآن
you would see that there was an amazing number
أمكنك رؤية أنه هناك عدد مدهش
of brain regions that were active while recalling that memory.
من مناطق الدماغ التي كانت نشطة بينما تذكرت تلك الذكرى.
Now one brain region that would be robustly active
الآن، من مناطق الدماغ التي تكون نشطة بقوة
in particular is called the hippocampus,
تحديداً، تسمى بالحصين [هيبوكامبس]،
which for decades has been implicated in processing
و التي لعقود كانت لها علاقة بتشكيل
the kinds of memories that we hold near and dear,
أنواع الذكريات المقربة إلينا،
which also makes it an ideal target to go into
و الذي يجعل الحصين هدف مثالي للوصول إليه
and to try and find and maybe reactivate a memory.
لمحاولة إيجاد و ربما لإعادة تفعيل ذاكرة.
XL: When you zoom in into the hippocampus,
شو: عندما تكبِّر الحصين،
of course you will see lots of cells,
بالطبع سوف تجد الكثير من الخلايا،
but we are able to find which cells are involved
لكن كنا قادرين أن نجد الخلايا المشاركة
in a particular memory,
في ذاكرة محددة،
because whenever a cell is active,
لأن كلما تكون هناك خلية نشطة،
like when it's forming a memory,
كما يحدث عند تشكيل ذاكرة،
it will also leave a footprint that will later allow us to know
سوف تترك أثر يسمح لنا أن نعرف
these cells are recently active.
أن هذه الخلايا كانت نشطة منذ قليل.
SR: So the same way that building lights at night
ستيف: فبنفس الطريقة التي تخبرك بها أضواء الشقق في الليل
let you know that somebody's probably working there at any given moment,
أنه على الأغلب يوجد شخص هناك يعمل في أي لحظة،
within a cell that are turned on
موجودة داخل الخلية، هذه المستشعرات تضيء
only when that cell was just working.
فقط عندما تكون هذه الخلية قد عملت للتو
They're sort of biological windows that light up
هي نوع من النوافذ البيولوجية التي تضيء
to let us know that that cell was just active.
لتعلمنا أن هذه الخلية كانت للتو نشطة.
and attached that to a switch to control the cells,
و توصيله بمفتاح للتحكم في الخلايا،
and we packed this switch into an engineered virus
و عبأناه في فيروسات معدَّلة
and injected that into the brain of the mice.
و حقنا ذلك في دماغ الفأر.
So whenever a memory is being formed,
فكلما تتكون ذاكرة،
any active cells for that memory
أي خلايا فعّالة في هذه الذاكرة
will also have this switch installed.
سوف تحتوي أيضاً على مفتاح التحكم هذا.
SR: So here is what the hippocampus looks like
ستيف: فهكذا يبدو شكل الحصين
The sea of blue that you see here
البحر الأزرق الذي ترونه هنا
are densely packed brain cells,
هو عبارة عن اكتظاظ للخلايا الدماغية
but the green brain cells,
لكن الخلايا الدماغية الخضراء،
the green brain cells are the ones that are holding on
الخلايا الدماغية الخضراء هي تلك التي تحمل
to a specific fear memory.
ذاكرة خوف محددة.
So you are looking at the crystallization
فأنت تنظر إلى تكوين
of the fleeting formation of fear.
الخوف.
You're actually looking at the cross-section of a memory right now.
أنت بالواقع تنظر إلى مقطع عرضي لذاكرة ما الآن.
XL: Now, for the switch we have been talking about,
شو: الآن، بالنسبة لمفتاح التحكم الذي كنّا نتحدث عنه،
ideally, the switch has to act really fast.
يجب أن يعمل المفتاح بسرعة كبيرة.
It shouldn't take minutes or hours to work.
ليس من المفترض أن يستغرق دقائق أو ساعات ليعمل.
It should act at the speed of the brain, in milliseconds.
يجب أن يعمل بنفس سرعة الدماغ، بالميللي ثانية.
SR: So what do you think, Xu?
ستيف: فما رأيك، شو؟
Could we use, let's say, pharmacological drugs
هل يمكننا استخدام، لنقول، أدوية
to activate or inactivate brain cells?
لنفعّل أو نثبّط خلايا الدماغ؟
XL: Nah. Drugs are pretty messy. They spread everywhere.
شو: لا. إن الأدوية فوضوية حقاً. إنها تنتشر في كل مكان.
And also it takes them forever to act on cells.
و أيضاً تستغرق وقتاً طويلاً لتؤثّر على الخلايا.
So it will not allow us to control a memory in real time.
لذا إنها لن تسمح لنا بالتحكم الآني بذاكرة ما.
So Steve, how about let's zap the brain with electricity?
حسناً ستيف، ما رأيك أن نعرّض الدماغ لصدمة كهربائية؟
SR: So electricity is pretty fast,
ستيف: حسناً، إن الكهرباء سريعة جداً،
but we probably wouldn't be able to target it
لكننا على الأغلب لن نستطيع توجيهها
to just the specific cells that hold onto a memory,
للخلايا المحددة المسؤولة عن الذاكرة،
and we'd probably fry the brain.
و على الأغلب سوف نقلي الدماغ.
XL: Oh. That's true. So it looks like, hmm,
شو: آه. إن ذلك صحيح. إذاً يبدو أن..
indeed we need to find a better way
حقاً إننا بحاجة أن نجد طريقة أفضل
to impact the brain at the speed of light.
لنؤثر على الدماغ بنفس سرعة الضوء.
SR: So it just so happens that light travels at the speed of light.
ستيف: و يصدف أن الضوء ينتقل بسرعة الضوء.
So maybe we could activate or inactive memories
فربما يمكننا أن ننشط أو نثبِّط الذكريات
by just using light --
باستخدام الضوء فقط --
XL: That's pretty fast.
شو: هذا سريع حقاً.
SR: -- and because normally brain cells
ستيف: -- و بما أن خلايا الدماغ
don't respond to pulses of light,
لا تستجيب بالعادة إلى نبضات الضوء
so those that would respond to pulses of light
فتلك التي سوف تستجيب
are those that contain a light-sensitive switch.
هي التي تملك مفتاح تحكم حساس للضوء.
Now to do that, first we need to trick brain cells
الآن لتنفيذ ذلك، أولاً يجب أن نتلاعب بالخلايا الدماغية
to respond to laser beams.
لتستجيب لأشعة الليزر.
XL: Yep. You heard it right.
شو: نعم. لقد ما سمعتوه صحيح.
We are trying to shoot lasers into the brain.
نحن نحاول أن نطلق أشعة ليزر على الدماغ.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
SR: And the technique that lets us do that is optogenetics.
ستيف: و التقنية التي تسمح لما بفعل ذلك هي تقنية الجينات الضوئية.
Optogenetics gave us this light switch that we can use
توفر لنا تقنية الجينات الضوئية مفاتيح التحكم الضوئية التي يمكننا استخدامها
to turn brain cells on or off,
لتشغيل و إطفاء خلايا الدماغ،
and the name of that switch is channelrhodopsin,
و اسم هذه المفاتيح هو "تشانيل رودوبسين" [بروتين ناقل في الأغشية]
seen here as these green dots attached to this brain cell.
تبدو هنا كنقط خضراء متصلة بالخلية الدماغية هذه.
You can think of channelrhodopsin as a sort of light-sensitive switch
يمكنك التفكير في ال"تشانيل رودوبسين" كنوع من المفاتيح الحساسة للضوء
that can be artificially installed in brain cells
التي يمكننا تثبيتها بشكل صناعي في خلايا الدماغ
so that now we can use that switch
بحيث نستطيع الآن استخدام ذلك المفتاح
to activate or inactivate the brain cell simply by clicking it,
لتنشيط أو تثبيط خلايا الدماغ ببساطة بالضغط عليه،
and in this case we click it on with pulses of light.
و في هذه الحالة نحن نضغط عليه بنبضات ضوئية.
XL: So we attach this light-sensitive switch of channelrhodopsin
شو: إذاً نحن نوصل هذا المفتاح الحساس للضوء من ال"تشانيل رودوبسين"
to the sensor we've been talking about
بالمستشعرات التي تكلمنا عنها
and inject this into the brain.
و نحقن ذلك في الدماغ
So whenever a memory is being formed,
فكلما تتكون ذاكرة،
any active cell for that particular memory
أي خلية نشطة في هذه الذاكرة
will also have this light-sensitive switch installed in it
سوف يكون لديها أيضاً هذا المفتاح الحساس للضوء مثبَّت لديها
so that we can control these cells
بحيث نستطيع التحكم بهذه الخلايا
by the flipping of a laser just like this one you see.
بومضة من الليزر كالذي ترونه.
SR: So let's put all of this to the test now.
ستيف: دعنا نختبر هذا كله الآن.
What we can do is we can take our mice
ما يمكننا فعله هو أخذ فئراننا
and then we can put them in a box that looks exactly like this box here,
و وضعهم في صندوق يشبه تماماً هذا الصندوق هنا،
and then we can give them a very mild foot shock
و ثم يمكننا إعطاءهم صعقة كهربائية طفيفة جداً
so that they form a fear memory of this box.
بحيث يكوّنون ذاكرة خوف من هذا الصندوق.
They learn that something bad happened here.
يتعلمون أن شيء سيّء قد حدث هنا.
Now with our system, the cells that are active
الآن مع نظامنا، الخلايا الفعالة
in the hippocampus in the making of this memory,
في تكوين هذه الذاكرة في الحصين،
only those cells will now contain channelrhodopsin.
فقط هذه الخلايا سوف تحتوي الآن على الـ "تشانيل رودوبسين"
XL: When you are as small as a mouse,
شو: عندما تكون صغير الحجم كالفأر،
it feels as if the whole world is trying to get you.
تشعر كأن العالم أجمع يكيد لك.
So your best response of defense
فأفضل استجابة دفاعية
is trying to be undetected.
هي محاولة التّخفّي
Whenever a mouse is in fear,
كلما يكون الفأر خائف،
it will show this very typical behavior
يظهر هذا النوع من السلوك النموذجي
by staying at one corner of the box,
بالبقاء في زاوية واحدة من الصندوق،
trying to not move any part of its body,
محاولاً ألّا يحرك أي جزء من جسمه،
and this posture is called freezing.
و هذه الوضعية تسمى بالتجمّد.
So if a mouse remembers that something bad happened in this box,
فإن تذكر فأر أن شيئاً سيّء قد حدث في هذا الصندوق،
and when we put them back into the same box,
و عندما نضعه مجدداً في نفس الصندوق،
it will basically show freezing
سوف يظهر وضعية التجمّد
because it doesn't want to be detected
لأنه لا يريد أن يتم كشفه
by any potential threats in this box.
بواسطة أي مصدر تهديد في هذا الصندوق.
SR: So you can think of freezing as,
ستيف: فيمكنك التفكير بالتجمد كالتالي،
you're walking down the street minding your own business,
أنت تسير في الشارع في حال سبيلك،
and then out of nowhere you almost run into
و فجأة تكاد تمر
an ex-girlfriend or ex-boyfriend,
بحبيبة سابقة أو حبيب سابق،
and now those terrifying two seconds
و في هتين الثانيتين المرعبتين
where you start thinking, "What do I do? Do I say hi?
تبدأ تفكر، "ماذا أفعل؟ هل أقول مرحباً؟
Do I shake their hand? Do I turn around and run away?
هل أصافحهم؟ هل أستدير و أهرب؟
Do I sit here and pretend like I don't exist?"
هل أجلس هناك و أتظاهر بعدم الوجود؟"
Those kinds of fleeting thoughts that physically incapacitate you,
هذا النوع من الأفكار العابرة التي تقيّد حركتك،
that temporarily give you that deer-in-headlights look.
التي تجعلك تبدو مرتبك لبرهة.
XL: However, if you put the mouse in a completely different
شو: لكن إن وضعت الفأر في صندوق
new box, like the next one,
جديد مختلف كلياً، مثل هذا،
it will not be afraid of this box
فإنه لن يكون خائف من هذا الصندوق
because there's no reason that it will be afraid of this new environment.
لأنه لا يوجد أي سبب لأن يخاف من هذه البيئة الجديدة.
But what if we put the mouse in this new box
لكن ماذا لو وضعنا الفأر في هذا الصندوق الجديد
but at the same time, we activate the fear memory
لكن في نفس الوقت، فعَّلنا ذاكرة الخوف
using lasers just like we did before?
باستخدام الليزر كما فعلنا سابقاً؟
Are we going to bring back the fear memory
هل سنسترجع ذاكرة الخوف
for the first box into this completely new environment?
من الصندوق الأول في هذه البيئة الجديدة كلياً؟
SR: All right, and here's the million-dollar experiment.
ستيف: حسناً، و هذه هي التجربة المنتظرة.
Now to bring back to life the memory of that day,
الآن لإسترجاع ذلك اليوم،
I remember that the Red Sox had just won,
أتذكر أن "رد سوكس" [فريق كرة القاعدة] قد ربح للتو،
it was a green spring day,
لقد كان يوم مخضر ربيعي،
perfect for going up and down the river
مثالي للتنزه بجانب النهر
and then maybe going to the North End
و ربما ثم الذهاب إلى "نورث إند" [حي في بوسطن]
to get some cannolis, #justsaying.
لشراء بعض ال"كانولي" [تحلية]، فقط أتصور.
Now Xu and I, on the other hand,
الآن شو و أنا، من ناحية أخرى،
were in a completely windowless black room
كنا في غرفة ذات ظلام دامس بدون نوافذ
not making any ocular movement that even remotely resembles an eye blink
لا نحرك عينينا أبداً و لا حتى نرمشهم
because our eyes were fixed onto a computer screen.
لأن أعيننا كانت متسمّرة على شاشة الكمبيوتر.
We were looking at this mouse here trying to activate a memory
كنّا ننظر إلى هذا الفأر هنا نحاول أن نفعّل ذاكرة
for the first time using our technique.
لأول مرة باستخدام تقنيتنا.
XL: And this is what we saw.
شو: و هذا ما رأيناه.
When we first put the mouse into this box,
في البداية عندما نضع الفأر في هذا الصندوق،
it's exploring, sniffing around, walking around,
يقوم بالاستكشاف، يشم ما حوله، يمشي في المكان،
minding its own business,
في حال سبيله،
because actually by nature,
لكن بالطبيعة،
mice are pretty curious animals.
الفئران حيوانات فضولية جداً.
They want to know, what's going on in this new box?
يريدون أن يعرفوا، ما الذي يجري في هذا الصندوق الجديد؟
It's interesting.
إنه مثير للاهتمام.
But the moment we turned on the laser, like you see now,
لكن بنفس اللحظة التي شغلنا فيها الليزر، كما ترون الآن،
all of a sudden the mouse entered this freezing mode.
فجأة دخل الفأر وضعية التجمد هذه.
It stayed here and tried not to move any part of its body.
لقد ظل واقفاً هنا و حاول ألا يحرك أي جزء من جسمه.
Clearly it's freezing.
يبدوا بوضوح أنه يتجمد.
So indeed, it looks like we are able to bring back
إذاً حقاً، يبدوا أننا قادرين أن نسترجع
the fear memory for the first box
ذاكرة الخوف من الصندوق الأول
in this completely new environment.
في هذه البيئة الجديدة كلياً.
While watching this, Steve and I
بينما كنَا نشاهد هذا، ستيف و أنا
are as shocked as the mouse itself.
كنا مصدومين بقدر الفأر نفسه.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So after the experiment, the two of us just left the room
إذاً بعد التجربة، خرجنا من الغرفة
without saying anything.
دون قول أي شيء.
After a kind of long, awkward period of time,
بعد فترة طويلة بعض الشيء، و غريبة،
Steve broke the silence.
ستيف كسر الصمت.
SR: "Did that just work?"
ستيف: "هل نجح ذلك للتو؟"
XL: "Yes," I said. "Indeed it worked!"
شو: قلت: "نعم". "حقاً لقد نجح!"
We're really excited about this.
تحمَسنا جداً لهذا.
And then we published our findings
و بعد ذلك نشرنا نتائجنا
in the journal Nature.
في دورية "نايتشر".
Ever since the publication of our work,
منذ نشر بحثنا،
we've been receiving numerous comments
نحن نتلقى العديد من التعليقات
from all over the Internet.
من حول الإنترنت.
Maybe we can take a look at some of those.
ربما يمكننا رؤية بعضها.
["OMGGGGG FINALLY... so much more to come, virtual reality, neural manipulation, visual dream emulation... neural coding, 'writing and re-writing of memories', mental illnesses. Ahhh the future is awesome"]
["ياااااااااااا إلهي و أخيراً.. الكثير سوف يتحقق، الواقع الافتراضي، التلاعب العصبي، محاكاة الأحلام البصرية.. التشفير العصبي، 'كتابة و إعادة كتابة الذكريات'، الأمراض العقلية. آه إنَّ المستقبل مبهر"]
SR: So the first thing that you'll notice is that people
ستيف: إذا أول شيء ستلاحظه هو أن الناس
have really strong opinions about this kind of work.
لديها آراء قوية في هذا النوع من الأبحاث.
Now I happen to completely agree with the optimism
الآن أنا أوافق تماماً على التفاؤل
of this first quote,
في هذا التعليق،
because on a scale of zero to Morgan Freeman's voice,
لأن على المقياس من الصفر إلى صوت "مورغان فريمان" [ممثل]،
it happens to be one of the most evocative accolades
هو واحد من أهم التشريفات
that I've heard come our way.
التي سمعتها موجهة إلينا
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But as you'll see, it's not the only opinion that's out there.
لكن كما سترون، إنه ليس الرأي الوحيد الموجود.
["This scares the hell out of me... What if they could do that easily in humans in a couple of years?! OH MY GOD WE'RE DOOMED"]
["هذا يخيفني جداً.. ماذا لو استطاعوا أن يفعلوا ذلك مع البشر بعد بضع سنوات؟! يا إلهي نحن هالكون"]
XL: Indeed, if we take a look at the second one,
شو: بالفعل، إن نظرنا إلى التعليق الثاني،
I think we can all agree that it's, meh,
أعتقد أننا كلنا نتفق أنه..
probably not as positive.
على الأغلب ليس إيجابي كالأول.
But this also reminds us that,
لكنه أيضاً يذكرنا أن،
although we are still working with mice,
على الرغم من أننا مازلنا نتعامل مع الفئران،
it's probably a good idea to start thinking and discussing
إنها على الأغلب فكرة جيدة أن نبدأ التفكير و مناقشة
about the possible ethical ramifications
العواقب الأخلاقية المحتملة
of memory control.
للتحكم بالذاكرة.
SR: Now, in the spirit of the third quote,
ستيف: الآن، في ضوء التعليق الثالث،
we want to tell you about a recent project that we've been
نريد أن نخبركم عن مشروع نعمل عليه مؤخراً
working on in lab that we've called Project Inception.
في المختبر و قد أسميناه مشروع بداية.
["They should make a movie about this. Where they plant ideas into peoples minds, so they can control them for their own personal gain. We'll call it: Inception."]
["يجب أن يصوروا فيلم عن هذا. حيث يزرعون الأفكار في أدمغة البشر، لكي يتحكموا بهم من أجل منافع شخصية. و سنسميه: بداية"]
So we reasoned that now that we can reactivate a memory,
ففكرنا أننا الآن نستطيع تنشيط ذاكرة،
what if we do so but then begin to tinker with that memory?
ماذا لو فعلنا ذلك مع التلاعب في هذه الذاكرة؟
Could we possibly even turn it into a false memory?
هل يمكننا حتى تحويلها لذاكرة خاطئة؟
XL: So all memory is sophisticated and dynamic,
شو: كل ذاكرة معقدة و ديناميكية،
but if just for simplicity, let's imagine memory
لكن فقط للتبسيط، دعنا نتخيل الذاكرة
as a movie clip.
كلقطة من فيلم.
So far what we've told you is basically we can control
ما أخبرناكم به حتى الآن هو أننا نستطيع التحكم
this "play" button of the clip
بزر "التشغيل" للقطة
so that we can play this video clip any time, anywhere.
بحيث نستطيع أن نشاهد هذا الفيديو في أي وقت، أي مكان.
But is there a possibility that we can actually get
لكن هل هنالك إمكانية أن نستطيع
inside the brain and edit this movie clip
الدخول إلى داخل الدماغ و تحرير لقطة الفيلم هذه؟
so that we can make it different from the original?
بحيث نستطيع جعلها مختلفة عن الأصل؟
Yes we can.
نعم نستطيع.
Turned out that all we need to do is basically
لقد تبين أن كل ما علينا فعله هو
reactivate a memory using lasers just like we did before,
إعادة تنشيط ذاكرة ما باستخدام الليرز كما فعلنا سابقاً،
but at the same time, if we present new information
لكن في نفس الوقت، إن قدمنا معلومات جديدة
and allow this new information to incorporate into this old memory,
و سمحنا لهذه المعلومات الجديدة أن تندمج مغ الذاكرة القديمة،
this will change the memory.
هذا سوف يغير الذاكرة.
It's sort of like making a remix tape.
إنه تقريباً مثل عمل شريط أغاني منوعة.
SR: So how do we do this?
ستيف: إذاً كيف نفعل هذا؟
Rather than finding a fear memory in the brain,
بدلاً من إيجاد ذاكرة خوف في الدماغ،
we can start by taking our animals,
نستطيع البدء بأخذ حيواناتنا،
and let's say we put them in a blue box like this blue box here
و وضعهم في صندوق أزرق كهذا
and we find the brain cells that represent that blue box
و وجدنا خلايا الدماغ التي تمثل هذا الصندوق الأزرق
and we trick them to respond to pulses of light
و جعلناهم يستجيبوا لنبضات ضوئية
exactly like we had said before.
تماماً كما ذكرنا سابقاً.
Now the next day, we can take our animals and place them
الآن في اليوم التالي، نستطيغ أخذ حيواناتنا و وضعهم
in a red box that they've never experienced before.
في صندوق أحمر لم يجربوه أبداً من قبل.
We can shoot light into the brain to reactivate
نستطيع أن نسقط الضوء على الدماغ لننشط
the memory of the blue box.
ذاكرة الصندوق الأزرق.
So what would happen here if, while the animal
إذاً ماذا قد يحدث هنا إن، بينما الحيوان
is recalling the memory of the blue box,
يتذكر الصندوق الأزرق،
we gave it a couple of mild foot shocks?
عرضنا قدميه لبضع صدمات كهربائية خفيفة؟
So here we're trying to artificially make an association
فنحن هنا نحاول أن نربط بشكل مصطنع
between the memory of the blue box
بين ذاكرة الصندوق الأزرق
and the foot shocks themselves.
و الصعقات الكهربائية للأقدام.
We're just trying to connect the two.
نحن فقط نحاول أن نربط الإثنين.
So to test if we had done so,
إذاً لنختبر إن كنّا قد حققنا ذلك،
we can take our animals once again
نستطيع أن نأخذ حيواناتنا مرة أخرى
and place them back in the blue box.
و أرجعناهم إلى الصندوق الأزرق.
Again, we had just reactivated the memory of the blue box
من جديد، لقد نشطنا ذاكرة الصندوق الأزرق
while the animal got a couple of mild foot shocks,
بينما تعرض الحيوان إلى بضع صعقات خفيفة للأقدام،
and now the animal suddenly freezes.
و الآن يتجمد الحيوان فجأة.
It's as though it's recalling being mildly shocked in this environment
كأنه يتذكر التعرض للصعق في هذه البيئة
even though that never actually happened.
على الرغم من عدم حدوث ذلك أبداً.
So it formed a false memory,
فإذاً قد تكونت ذاكرة خاطئة،
because it's falsely fearing an environment
لأنه بالخطأ أصبح يخاف بيئة
where, technically speaking,
حيث، عملياً،
nothing bad actually happened to it.
لم يحدث أي شيء سيء فيها.
XL: So, so far we are only talking about
شو: إذاً، حتى الآن نحن فقط نتكلم عن
this light-controlled "on" switch.
مفتاح "التشغيل" الحساس للضوء.
In fact, we also have a light-controlled "off" switch,
في الحقيقة، نحن لدينا أيضاً مفتاح "إطفاء" حساس للضوء،
and it's very easy to imagine that
و من السهل جداً تصور أن
by installing this light-controlled "off" switch,
بتثبيت مفتاح "الإطفاء" هذا،
we can also turn off a memory, any time, anywhere.
نستطيع أن نطفئ ذاكرة، في أي وقت، و أي مكان.
So everything we've been talking about today
إذاً كل شيء تكلمنا عنه اليوم
is based on this philosophically charged principle of neuroscience
هو عن هذا المبدأ الفلسفي في علم الأعصاب
that the mind, with its seemingly mysterious properties,
أن العقل، مع خواصه التي تبدو غامضة،
is actually made of physical stuff that we can tinker with.
هو في الحقيقة مكون من أشياء فيزيائية يمكننا تعديلها.
SR: And for me personally,
ستيف: و بالنسبة لي شخصياً،
I see a world where we can reactivate
إنني أرى عالماً حيث نستطيع إعادة تفعيل
any kind of memory that we'd like.
أي نوع من الذاكرة نرغب.
I also see a world where we can erase unwanted memories.
إنني إيضاً أرى عالماً حيث نستطيع محو الذكريات الغير مرغوب فيها.
Now, I even see a world where editing memories
الآن، إنني حتى أرى عالماً حيث تعديل الذكريات
is something of a reality,
شيء من الواقع،
because we're living in a time where it's possible
لأننا نعيش في زمن حيث من الممكن
to pluck questions from the tree of science fiction
نزع أسئلة من شجرة الخيال العلمي
and to ground them in experimental reality.
و زرعهم في واقع بحثي.
XL: Nowadays, people in the lab
شو: في هذه الأيام الناس في المختبر
and people in other groups all over the world
و الناس في مجموعات أخرى حول العالم
are using similar methods to activate or edit memories,
يستخدمون طرق مماثلة لتنشيط أو تعديل الذكريات،
whether that's old or new, positive or negative,
سواء أكانت قديمة أم حديثة، إيجابية أم سلبية،
all sorts of memories so that we can understand
كل أنواع الذكريات لكي نستطيع فهم
how memory works.
كيف تعمل الذاكرة.
SR: For example, one group in our lab
ستيف: مثلاً، أحد المجموعات في مختبرنا
was able to find the brain cells that make up a fear memory
استطاعت إيجاد خلايا الدماغ التي تشكل ذاكرة الخوف
and converted them into a pleasurable memory, just like that.
و حولتها إلى ذاكرة محببة، بهذه بساطة.
That's exactly what I mean about editing these kinds of processes.
هذا بالضبط ما أعنية بتعديل هذه الأنواع من العمليات.
Now one dude in lab was even able to reactivate
الآن أحدهم في المختبر كان قادراً أن يعيد تفعيل
which rumor has it is a pleasurable experience.
يقال إنها تجربة ممتعة.
XL: Indeed, we are living in a very exciting moment
شو: بالفعل، نحن نعيش لحظة مثيرة جداً
where science doesn't have any arbitrary speed limits
حيث لا يوجد حدود لسرعة العلم
but is only bound by our own imagination.
بل هو يعتمد فقط على مخيلتنا.
SR: And finally, what do we make of all this?
ستيف: و أخيراً، ما نحن صانعون بهذا كله؟
How do we push this technology forward?
كيف يمكننا دفع هذه التقنية إلى الأمام؟
These are the questions that should not remain
هذه هي الأسئلة التي يجب ألا تبقى
just inside the lab,
في داخل المختير،
and so one goal of today's talk was to bring everybody
فمن أهداف حديث اليوم كان إخبار الجميع
up to speed with the kind of stuff that's possible
بالأشياء التي أصبحت ممكنة
in modern neuroscience,
في علم الأعصاب الحديث،
but now, just as importantly,
لكن الآن، بقدر أهمية ذلك،
to actively engage everybody in this conversation.
من المهم إشراك الجميع في هذا الحديث.
So let's think together as a team about what this all means
إذاً دعنا نفكر سوياً كفريق عما يعنيه هذا كله
and where we can and should go from here,
و إلى أين يمكننا و يجب علينا أن ننطلق من هنا،
because Xu and I think we all have
لأن شو و أنا نعتقد أن جميعنا لديه
some really big decisions ahead of us.
بعض القرارات الكبيرة حقاً بانتظارنا.
Thank you. XL: Thank you.
شكراً. شو: شكراً.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)